Guide to the John Galsworthy letters to Professor William Sadler, 1911-1914 MS 317
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
John Galsworthy letters to Professor William Sadler
1911-1914
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Galsworthy, John
MS 317
0.1 Linear Feet (1 folder of 11 letters)
This collection consists of 11 letters written between the years 1911 and 1914 by John Galsworthy to Professor William Sadler. Most of the letters contain travel plans and arrangements for meeting each other; however, several of the letters comment on current events, including Galsworthy's response to Sadler on the outbreak of World War I.
Biographical Note
John Galsworthy (1867-1933) was a playwright and novelist educated at Harrow and New College, Oxford. He was called to the bar (Lincoln's Inn) in 1890 and published his early novels under the pseudonym of John Sinjohn. He wrote The Man of Property (1906) and The Forsyte Saga (1922) along with many other works including the trilogy A Modern Comedy in 1929. Some of his more successful plays include: The Silver Box (1906), Justice (1910), and The Skin Game (1920). John Galsworthy was awarded the Order of Merit in 1919 and the Nobel Prize in 1932.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of 11 letters, written between the years 1911 and 1914, from John Galsworthy to Professor William Sadler. The identity of the latter figure remains unknown. The letters usually contain information regarding travel plans and arrangements for meeting each other. Several of the letters comment on current events, including Galsworthy's response to Sadler on the outbreak of World War I.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored onsite at the Woodson Research Center.
Acquisition Information
This collection was a gift donated by the Friends' Fund (Whittington gift) in 1953.
Index Terms
Subjects
Travel; World War (1914-1918)
Document Types
letters (correspondence)
- Series I: Correspondence, 46548
  - 27 February 1911; John Galsworthy to William Sadler. Informing him of the new dates of his plans to travel to Manchester., 46559 (Folder 1)
  - 28 February 1911; John Galsworthy to William Sadler. Arrangements for their meeting., 46558 (Folder 1)
  - 13 March 1911; John Galsworthy to William Sadler. Further arrangements., 46557 (Folder 1)
  - 21 March ?; John Galsworthy to William Sadler. "I would have liked to come, but I fear it won't be possible. So sorry.", 46556 (Folder 1)
  - 16 November 1911; John Galsworthy to William Sadler. Giving advice about joining a society (probably on penal reform)., 46555 (Folder 1)
  - 30 May 1912; John Galsworthy to William Sadler. Letter remarking on a contemporary literary exchange., 46554 (Folder 1)
  - 26 October 1913; John Galsworthy to William Sadler. Discussing the arrangements for the performance of strife., 46553 (Folder 1)
  - 4 November 1913; John Galsworthy to William Sadler. Thanks for an article received – contains some mention of Galsworthy's thoughts on events in India., 46552 (Folder 1)
  - 3 December 1913; John Galsworthy to William Sadler. A letter of thanks following a performance in Leeds., 46551 (Folder 1)
  - 7 December 1913; John Galsworthy to William Sadler. Thanks for some Coleridge poems and other items of business., 46550 (Folder 1)
  - 3 December 1914; John Galsworthy to William Sadler., 46549 (Folder 1)
    General
    Responding to news of the war. "The best thing about this war is the lie it gives to the talk about the degeneration of man through peace, humanism, and the arts." Also containing some thoughts on the "new religion" and how it is "exemplified…in our irreligious Tommies."